Guide to the Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) Office of the Treasurer Records, 1891-1924 UA.10.01.0002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) Office of the Treasurer records
1891-1924
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.). Office of the Treasurer
UA.10.01.0002
6 Linear Feet
In the early years of Trinity College, the President handled most financial affairs with assistance and guidance from the Board of Trustees. When the College moved to Durham in 1892, one of the trustees, Durham businessman Virginius Ballard, filled the post of College Treasurer and served until 1898. President John C. Kilgo took over the task until 1907. At that point, it appears that an office of Treasurer was formally established, as Dallas W. Newsom is listed in the Catalog as Treasurer. The collection includes ledgers and ledger sheets, cash books, journals, insurance policies, bonds, titles, leases, building and service contracts, correspondence, reports and other records, with bulk dates of 1910-1924. Records from 1891 concerning the Durham campus and buildings are also included.
2,500 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) Office of the Treasurer Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1989.
Biographical/Historical note
In the early years of Trinity College, the President handled most financial affairs with assistance and guidance from the Board of Trustees. When the College moved to Durham in 1892, one of the trustees, Durham businessman Virginius Ballard, filled the post of College Treasurer and served until 1898. President John C. Kilgo took over the task until 1907. At that point, it appears that an office of Treasurer was formally established, as Dallas W. Newsom is listed in the Catalog as Treasurer. He held the position until 1923, when C. B. Markham, a former professor of Mathematics, was appointed to the office.
Scope and Contents note
The collection includes ledgers and ledger sheets, cash books, journals, insurance policies, bonds, titles, leases, building and service contracts, correspondence, reports and other records, with bulk dates of 1910-1924. Records from 1891 concerning the Durham campus and buildings are also included. Most of the pages are brittle and should be handled with care.
Related Material
Office of the [Duke] University Treasurer records, 1893-1979
Duke University Archives
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- Buildings; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- Administration; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- History; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- Finance; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.). Office of the Treasurer; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.). Office of the Treasurer
- Subject Files
  - Construction on Administration Building and Proposal to tear down Old Main, 1910 (Box 1)
  - Construction of Academic Building, Athletic Grounds account, specs for dismantling Old Main (prior to the fire), 1910 (Box 1)
  - Construction of Kilgo residence (Box 1)
  - Construction of East Dormitory, 1910 (Box 1)
  - Grading and Macadamizing of Racetrack and Academic Building, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Landscaping of Campus, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Financial Report of Dining Hall and Alspaugh Hall, 1920-1921 (Box 1)
  - Faculty and Staff, wages and lists of names, 1919, 1922-1923 (Box 1)
  - General Education Board, 1920 (Box 1)
  - General Alumni Fund, 1923 (Box 1)
  - Duke Fund for Ministers, 1919 (Box 1)
  - General Loan Fund, 1912-1920 (Box 1)
  - Southgate Memorial Fund, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Trinity Endowment Fund, 1912-1917 (Box 1)
  - Form Letters on Delinquent Student Accounts, 1922-1923 (Box 1)
  - Winifred Quinton Holton Award, 1919 (Box 1)
  - Federal Board for Vocational Education, 1920-1922 (Box 1)
  - Student Letters (general) (Box 1)
  - Commencement Bibles and Diplomas (Box 1)
  - Black Employees, 1913-1914 (Box 1)
  - Trinity Bell, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Insurance, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Steel Plate Engraving of Braxton Craven, 1915 (Box 1)
  - Declamation Contest, 1913 (Box 1)
  - Clubs and Societies, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Library and Library Donors, 1913-1921 (Box 1)
  - Furnishings, 1914 (Box 1)
  - A Statement of the Executive Committee of the Alumni Association to Graduates and Friends of Trinity College, circa 1918 (Box 1)
  - Student Finances, 1925 (Box 1)
  - Southgate Memorial Fund, 1921 (Box 1)
  - Services, boarding houses, selling coal, barber shop, check cashing, 1916 (Box 1)
  - Supplies, confiscations, shortages, strikes, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Scholarships, 1915 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1916, 1919 (Box 1)
  - World War I, soldiers, students, Veteran's Bureau, 1916-1917 (Box 1)
  - William Francis Gill Memorial Fund, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Employees, staff, student workers, blacks, 1919 (Box 1)
  - 1913 Class Pledge (Box 1)
  - General Business, 1916 (Box 1)
  - Gymnasium, completion and enlargement, 1923, 1925 (Box 1)
  - Washington Duke Building, collapse, 1891 (Box 1)
  - Commencement Expenses, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Estimated Income, 1916-1919 (Box 1)
  - Inventory of office furnishings destroyed by fire, 1911 January 4 (Box 2)
  - Press, 1922 (Box 2)
  - President's Reports on Trinity College to Trustees and Western NC Conferences, 1897-1899, 1909, 1911-1917 (Box 2)
  - US Veterans Bureau, Contracts and Vouchers, 1923 (Box 2)
  - Insurance, 1909, 1920-1921, 1923-1924 (Box 2)
  - Southgate Memorial Fund, 1921-1923 (Box 2)
  - Construction Improvements, 1910-1923 (Box 2)
  - Student Activity (academic), 1911 (Box 2)
  - Student Activity (financial), 1911-1924 (Box 2)
  - Student Activity (non-academic), 1911-1920 (Box 2)
  - Requests and/or bids for service to Trinity, 1918-1923 (Box 2)
  - Advertisements of Trinity College, 1915-1918, 1922-1923 (Box 2)
  - Bills (debts and payments), 1911-1922 (Box 2)
  - Samuel Mordecai (law school), 1922-1924 (Box 2)
  - Administration, faculty salaries, 1910-1923 (Box 2)
  - Titles, Leases, Deeds (stock activity), 1914-1924 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1919 (Box 2)
  - Endowment, Pledges, 1911-1923 (Box 2)
  - Gymnasium Fund and Construction, 1916-1924 (Box 2)
  - Donations/Gifts to Trinity College, 1910-1919, 1923 (Box 2)
  - Report, 1905-1906 (Box 3)
  - Financial Reports, 1910-1923 (Box 3)
  - Annual Financial Reports, 1910-1911, 1913-1914 (Box 3)
  - Annual Financial Reports and Miscellaneous Reports, Trinity Park School, 1910-1916 (Box 3)
  - Report to N.C. Conference, 1912 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Financial Reports, 1914-1919 (Box 3)
  - Audit, 1917 (Box 3)
  - Annual Financial Reports, 1915-1918 (Box 3)
  - Trinity Park School Reports, 1913-1919 (Box 3)
  - Financial Statement, 1919 (Box 3)
  - Statistical Report for Methodist Church, South, circa 1919 (Box 3)
  - Financial Statement, 1921 (Box 3)
  - Audit, 1924 (Box 3)
- Ledgers
  - Student Loan, Scholarship and Endowed Special Funds, 1899-1910 (Box 4)
  - Student Loan, Scholarship and Endowed Special Funds, 1909-1923 (Box 4)
  - Washington Duke Fund Subscriptions, 1905-1908 (Box 4)
  - Student Army Training Corps Reimbursement Statement, 1918-1919 (Box 5)
  - Southgate Memorial Subscriptions, 1920-1924 (Box 5)
  - General Endowment Subscriptions, 1912-1914 (Box 5)
  - Stock Records, 1909-1913 (Box 5)
  - Lock Box Records, circa 1911 (Box 5)
  - Record of Coal Shipments, 1910-1924 (Box 5)
  - Athletic Fund Records, 1912-1918 (Box 5)
  - Gym Building Subscriptions, 1871-1920 (Box 5)
  - South Atlantic Publishing Company, 1910-1918 (Box 6)
  - South Atlantic Publishing Company, 1918-1923 (Box 6)
  - South Atlantic Publishing Company Stock Records, 1911 (Box 6)
  - Scholarship Records, 1900-1913 (Box 7)
  - Stock/Inventory Records, 1899-1913 (Box 7)
  - Student and Faculty Financial Records, 1897-1920 (Box 7)
  - Student Financial Records, 1922-1923 (Box 7)
  - Mess Hall Records, 1918-1921 (Box 7)
  - Mess Hall Records, 1919-1921 (Box 7)